<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preacht in Madrid, July 4, 1666. s.n. occasioned by the sad and much lamented death of his late Excellency Sir Richard Fanshaw Knight and Baronet ... / by Henry Bagshaw.</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Henry, 1632-1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9009</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11806735</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11806735</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49461</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49461)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 806:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preacht in Madrid, July 4, 1666. s.n. occasioned by the sad and much lamented death of his late Excellency Sir Richard Fanshaw Knight and Baronet ... / by Henry Bagshaw.</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Henry, 1632-1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Beadle and T. Collins, and are to be sold at their shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fanshawe, Richard, --  Sir, 1608-1666.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XII, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49461:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRIMAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Tho. Tomkym</hi> R. R. in Chriſto Patri ac Domino Domino <hi>Gilberto</hi> Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Providentia Archi-Epiſcopo Cantuarienſi a Sacris Domeſticis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49461:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHT IN MADRID, <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LY</hi> 4. 1666. S. N. OCCASIONED By the Sad and much Lamented Death of his late Excellency Sir <hi>RICHARD FAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHAW,</hi> Knight and Baronet, of his Majeſties Moſt Honourable Privy Council, and his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador in Ordinary to that COURT. Where falling Sick of a Violent Feaver, <hi>June</hi> 14th —66. He ended his Life the 26th day of that Moneth; in the Third Year of his Negotiation in that place, and the 59th Year of his AGE. By <hi>HENRY BAGSHAW,</hi> M. A. Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of <hi>Chriſt-Church Oxon,</hi> and his late Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies Chaplain in that EMBASSIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. Beadle</hi> and <hi>T. Collins,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shop at the <hi>Middle-Temple-Gate</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49461:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49461:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable my Lady <hi>FAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHAW,</hi> the Widow of his late Excellency my Lord Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador <hi>FANSHAW.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HOw ready I am to receive your Commands, but withall how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate in obeying them, may be eaſily judged by the coming forth of this Treatiſe; where I find I have only made my weakneſs publick, when I intended ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and being ſo much divided betwixt my duty to the Dead, and my obligations to the living, yet I am in neither able to pay. However I may preſume to venture the Worlds tryal in ſubjects of this nature, where I have ample Merit and great vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to deſcribe: for ſo men can charge me with poverty of words, but not with falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood:
<pb facs="tcp:49461:3"/>and though my Labours be mean, yet I know ſuch a Fate attends Worth, that it not only ſecures its own Fame, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects others that ſpeak of it. To tell your Ladiſhip whom I deſign by this, is to injure my Lords Memory, and your goodneſs; ſince both of you require from me a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular acknowledgement, though both be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove my testimony. I ſhould not here be willing to waken your griefs, nor recall to your remembrance paſt accidents, were I not ſufficiently convinced of your Faith in an affliction. This is a School, wherein you have been long with my Lord bred up; but whereas it might be imputed to the ſtrength of your love, that you could with him go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern all other misfortunes, it muſt be now meerly aſcribed to the ſtrength of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you can without him conquer the laſt. A ſevere Blow! ſenſibly felt by look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers on, but much more by your ſelf, that placed all your glory in his life: and yet to be able to kiſs the Rod, in all that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs
<pb facs="tcp:49461:3"/>of paſſion, which both your Sex and affection had raiſed, this argues a high temper of a Chriſtian; and makes me: doubt which is greater, the loſs, or your conſtancy in bearing it. Yet that courage you ſhow in ſuffering, is not more eminent, than the Nobleneſſe of your cares; which as they ſignally appeared in my Lords life time, ſo afterwards in your performance of all rights to his body; when you bore along through ſtrange Lands that Image of Sorrow, as if you would have an exerciſe of your love and your patience together. This was a Travel taught Friends Grief, and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Reverence; when they reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Greatneſs of the Perſon there repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and the Piety of the Conveyer; that the Wiſdome of a State ſhould be ſhut up in a Hearſe, and the Joyes of your Ladiſhip there encloſed. But there are other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars I could mention, wherein you are as nearly concerned: for whatever praiſe is due to a Devout Life, to an Exemplary
<pb facs="tcp:49461:4"/>Diſcipline, to a Loyal Love, or a Reſolute Faith, that your Ladiſhip may juſtly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge: of all which I could give the world pregnant proofs, but that I know, as it is the comfort of your grief to read my Lords <hi>Character,</hi> ſo 'tis the affliction of your Virtue to read your own. Therefore laying aſide this Theme in compliance to your will, yet in what relates to my ſelf I ſhall heg leave to publiſh to the World the great ſenſe I have of thoſe many favours I have received both from my Lord, and your Ladiſhip: who have alwayes lived with an equal love as to your ſelves, and with as equal a concern to oblige others; amongst whom none more reckons himſelf a Debtor than</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam</salute>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips moſt Obliged, Faithful Servant,<hi>Henry Bagſhaw.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49461:4"/>
            <head>A Funeral SERMON Preached in <hi>MADRID, July</hi> 4. 1666. At the Interment of Sir <hi>Richard Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhawe,</hi> his Majeſties Ambaſſador there.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HEB. 12.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now no Chaſtening for the preſent ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be joyous, but grievous; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, afterwards it yieldeth the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſs to them which are exerciſed thereby.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Diſcipline of breeding up Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans under a Scourge, and the way of planting a Church by laying its Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in Tears, are Methods ſo little tempting in themſelves, that they have no virtue to raiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49461:5"/>Followers: no more than Fire and Sword ſent by an Enemy can people Towns, which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly deſign'd to deſtroy the Inhabitants. But if you look up to the Soveraign Maſter of that Diſcipline, and the Glorious Bleſſing annext to that way of planting, all the ſeeming horrours in Religion are remov'd: The Whip Chriſt now uſes, drives Man into the Temple, that would not enter it before; the Death he denounces, prepares mans way for a Crown, that would not otherwiſe receive it; ſo that we may joyfully walk in a weeping Track, that leads us to a Grave, and a Grave open'd by our Saviour for a Triumph. 'Tis this Diſcipline the Apoſtle commends throughout this Epiſtle to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Jews ſcattered in the world; who needed an extraordinary light to diſcover the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Sons in ſuch a Diſpenſation, as being acquainted before with no other inheritance in this life, but that of Temporal Promiſes, and therefore thought it Baſtardy to ſuffer. Which Opinion of theirs, he confutes in the ſixth, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, and eighth verſes of this Chapter, and clearing to them the Doctrine of the Croſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms them in a new Principle of Goſpel-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: as in the words of my Text—<hi>Now no chaſtening for the preſent ſeemeth to be joyous, but grievous; nevertheleſs, afterwards it yieldeth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49461:5"/>the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſs to them which are exerciſed thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words contain in them theſe parts:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The unpleaſant Nature of Chaſtiſement to mans apprehenſion: <hi>Now no Chaſtening ſeemeth to be joyous, but grievous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The time this unpleaſantneſs laſts, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for the preſent; which indeed is no time, but an inſtant, that dies with naming it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The end and reward of Chaſtiſement; <hi>It yieldeth afterwards the peaceable fruit of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Qualification of the perſons that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it; they are ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; we ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it exercis'd; but it ſignifies ſuch that are approv'd and try'd in all the Combats of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Men, that have got art and ſtrength by their frequent meetings of that Adverſary, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel its force, and foil all its deſigns. I ſhall not proſecute theſe parts as they lie thus ſeverally, but form out of them all, theſe two Propoſitions which ſhall be the ſubject of my enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>Prop. 1. <hi>That Gods correcting hand, while it inflicts the blow, ſeems rather to carry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in it, than Mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prop 2. <hi>That the end of that blow to the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſufferer, is a high reward of Eternal Peace and repoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49461:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That Gods correcting hand, while it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts the blow, ſeems rather to carry Weight in it, than Mercy.</hi> Senſe (which is mans neareſt Neighbour while he lives in this world) is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the higheſt Favourite he loves to conſult with: 'Tis Senſe reports to him all accidents without, and according to the affections of Senſe is he wrought upon. Thoſe two Paſſions that are in us, Joy and Grief, have hence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the Original of their motion: Joy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a ſoft, Grief from a hard impreſſion, objects make upon our ſenſes; whence we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this thing to be joyous, the other thing to be grievous, from the different manner of its ſtroak; without taking farther information from Reaſon, whoſe Verdict were it heard, both thoſe ſtroaks would be counted indifferent to the ſoul. 'Twas this life of Senſe <hi>Job</hi> led,
<note place="margin">Job Cap. 3.</note> when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of his wounds; this life of Senſe <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> led,
<note place="margin">Eſther 5.9.</note> when he rejoyced in his proſperity; but the judgement of them both was fallacious; for neither was <hi>Job</hi> miſerable in his Smart, nor <hi>Haman</hi> happy in his Revels; to the one God ſhowed no Enmity, to the other no Friendſhip; nay, had they both reflected on the ends and conſequences of thoſe two States, <hi>Job</hi>'s chaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had been joyous to him, as the ſores were to <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom: <hi>Hamans</hi> height
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49461:6"/>mournful, as ſuch Proſpects are, where only Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution is ſeen. But Senſe bearing ſway in the beſt of Gods people, affliction is thereupon ill painted to their view, and temporal loſſes ſtrangely repreſented; and that upon three ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe of the ſeeming violence and breach they make upon Nature. Nature, that inclines us to Self-preſervation, ſpurs us on to a deſire of all good, in which that Intereſt is ſecured; whence Friends, Riches, Honours, and the like, have a value ſet on them, as Props that contribute to the ſtrength of our being. If therefore any of theſe goods ſhould be loſt, man is preſently apt to cry out, as if ſome limb of his happineſs were cut off, and his very being weakned by that change. And this Opinion, how imperfect our ſtate is in the want of theſe, the beſt are liable to entertain; being ready to fancy, life is not that which is maintained by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpirits, but by goods without us; and that to the perfection of our form, is neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite the aſſiſtance of another. Thus Man, that has a Power given of moving himſelf, and an infinite good propoſed to him for to ſill and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect all his Faculties, yet yields to be governed by low outward principles: and (ſuch is his corruption) he takes up Maximes concerning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49461:7"/>the ſufficiency of temporal things; which beget love in him, and adherence of mind: and ſo reſting upon thoſe Reeds, no wonder they pierce him with breaking. Hence the Soul can Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reliſh no trouble; for it appears deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to its bliſs; till Grace comes, and gives a new appetite; inſtilling into our minds a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Notion of happineſs; namely, ſuch that conſiſts not in preſent delights, but in a future Viſion; not in periſhing comforts, but in an Eternal Good; not in ſcattered Rayes, but in a full Sun: then Trouble (which was ſo harſh Phyſick to the old man) becomes agreeable to our deſires,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.12. Rom. 8.17.</note> becauſe the ſame Grace tells us, 'tis a means of purchaſing that perfection. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have this enlightening, man can only tend an inferiour good, and therefore muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily loathe an affliction as the diſturber of it.</p>
            <p>In this juncture 'tis Satans cuſtome treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly to invade us, as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> did the <hi>Sichemites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34.25.</note> when they were in their pain, and lay under the greateſt ſmart of their wounds: And with the like eaſe he prevails over the Soul, as theſe Brethren did over the Bodies of that people, by timing his aſſault, and guiding all the edge of his force againſt the weakneſs of the party. Now nothing ſo much diſables the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49461:7"/>Soul, nor expoſes it more to a ſurprize, than this violent paſſion of Sorrow: Luſt (though pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful) yet leaves Reaſon ſtill ſuch a Command, ſo as to check and controul it: Fear (though weak) yet leaves us ſo much ſpirit as to make us avoid danger; Deſpair (though ghaſtly) yet gives boldneſſe to encounter it; but Grief de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voures the underſtanding, cloſes up the heart, and ſo diſ-ſpirits the whole man, that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates himſelf to his calamity. 'Twas the height of this paſſion, ſo dull'd Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that it laid all their courage and devotion aſleep, at ſuch a time, when they ſhould have watched their Maſter;
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.43.</note> 'Twas the height of this paſſion corrupted <hi>Martha</hi>'s Faith,
<note place="margin">John 11.39.</note> when the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined ſmell of a Grave (where her Brother had lain for four daies) work'd more with her to believe his utter loſs, than the Divinity of a Saviour to hope the mercy of a recovery. With that apprehenſion all her faculties were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred, and Chriſts Preſence with all his Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles forgotten; as if the Arm of his Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence could not reach the dead, and Corruption were an Inheritance ſo Entail'd, that the Prince of Life could not alter it. But when once the Stone was removed, the Word given out, and that Word anſwered by her Brothers riſing, then her Faith with him revives: Which Figure of a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49461:8"/>future Reſurrection proving actually her cure, we ought all to contemplate, and apply to our ſelves, that we may be Maſters of the like trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe of the Cloud they ſeemingly caſt upon Providence; and this is a violence offer'd to Religion. The evil of ſin (which man brought into the world by the abuſe of his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will) has not ſo much occaſioned a Diſpute concerning Providence, as the evil of ſuffering, where man only is paſſive, and God properly the Inflicter. As to the firſt, Man bears the blame of that <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> by reaſon of the guilt he has contracted in miſimploying his faculties, which he had freedome to govern: As to the ſecond (ſince God is the cauſe of it) the merit of mans actions is enquired into, that thence a Reaſon might be alledged, why the Party ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers. This Merit of actions, when man is not ſatisfied in, he is thereupon apt to queſtion the order of a Supreme, and impute to Chance the building of the Univerſe, becauſe its Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment appears confuſed. Hence the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements of good men have been the old Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments Atheiſme has uſed to fix its ſeat in the world; and the Rod they were ſmitten with, has prov'd a Weapon in its hand to wound the Divinity of the Corrector. And indeed the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49461:8"/>Notions we have of Juſtice (an Attribute ſo Eſſential to the Godhead) ſeem much to ſuffer in their affliction; ſince it implies an unequal diſtribution of things, where Virtue is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſht by a Reward; and conſequently Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice it ſelf is doubted of in the Creator, as we queſtion the true reſemblance of that Piece, where the proportions are not diſcerned. Were there eyes in thoſe Wheels above, that turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this world, and order joyn'd with their noyſe to ſweeten the Motion, why then ſhould Vice get ſooneſt the Top, and Piety lye under? But if it chance to aſcend, why ſhould its aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent be with greater toil, and its downfall more ſudden, before the midſt of its courſe be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht? Can Gods care be ſeen in the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinners, or his goodneſſe in breaking his own Image? If he be careful of the world, let him waſh off the ſpots; if good, let him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve its Beauty; but to govern Affairs other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then his Attributes ſeem to promiſe, to let Darkneſſe overcome Light, and Guilt triumph in the ruines of Innocence, this affords the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt a plauſible Theme, when he declaims a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Providence, and gives his Wit a freſh Sting to perſecute Chriſtianity. Neither does the Atheiſt only take glad notice of this ſtrange Adminiſtration,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.14. Pſal. 10</note> but the Devil farther improves
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49461:9"/>it, to make his Votaries more ſure; for he builds them a Fabrick of viſible good, plants the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of his Kingdome to the eye,
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.8.</note> that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity only ſets before the Faith of its Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers. And as the preſent croſſes of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have much furthered the impiety of the looker on, ſo they beget immediately a quick ſenſe in the ſufferer, who reflects upon his own integrity, and therefore is prone to queſtion the hand that afflicts him. What does God act the part of a Judge, or a Soveraign in correcting me? If it be Soveraignty I muſt ſubmitto, alas there is no lovelineſs in that Attribute; for Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er conſidered without its Rule, can only be looked upon as Tyrannical and Oppreſſive; like a great Sea let looſe upon Land, that never di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides its ſtream with reſpect to the Soil, but co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers every part with an equal Deluge; if it be the Sentence of a Judge I muſt ſubmit to, where are its meaſures to ſhow the Equity of his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal? In what Balance are my actions weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſuch a portion of ill ſhould be laid in the Scales, which many a hainous Malefactor never knows? Thus the good man diſputes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the preſent touch of the Rod, and almoſt argues himſelf into Infidelity; ſtumbling fouly over thoſe ſtones the world throws at him, and making them at firſt cauſes of his fall, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49461:9"/>he turns afterwards to be Inſtruments of his Martyrdome. For Faith being once ſhaken, cannot in an inſtant recover its ſtrength; by degrees it muſt faſten in the ſoul, and be able to ſtand the Tempeſt; but when once 'tis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by time, and ſetled by deliberate Acts, it ſtops all farther complaint, and puts an end to the Objection.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe of the remoteneſſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that ſhould ſupport the Soul under that adverſity. In worldly Races men (that ſtrive for Maſtery) have a double advantage above the Chriſtian, in that they all know the fixt limits of their courſe, and ſee the Garland they run for; by knowing their courſe they are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their flight; by ſeeing their Crown, they breathe nothing but Victory. But we (that have rough wayes to travel in, and know not how far they tend; that have a Garland to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for, but are not able to make a diſcovery) may eaſily faint and be diſcouraged under the weight of ſome preſſures. How uncertain to us our Race is, will appear, becauſe our times are taken from us into Gods hand, and our ends reſerved to his own knowledge; how dark our neward is, will appear, both from conſidering the Nature of this Reward, (which is ſpiritual) and the manner of its conveyance (which only
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49461:10"/>Death helps us to) ſo that we muſt march through a gloomy walk to inviſible glory. 'Tis true, our ſtate under the Goſpel is much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> to whom life and immortality were not ſo clearly brought to light, neither by the plain Letter of the Text, nor by examples; both which we enjoy in the fulneſſe of Evidence, to confirm and ſettle us in that Article: however the unhappineſſe of that life is ſtill unknown; and though in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral we may be better grounded to believe, yet the Nature of thoſe joyes we as little diſcern. But ſuppoſe we had eyes ſo piercing as to ſee our Bliſſe, yet the vaſt ſeparation of its Seat cools many times the zeal of a Chriſtian; eſpecially when he labours under a preſent pain, which requires a neer object of ſuccour. Now Heaven and Glory are two Lights ſet afar off; whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence is not ſo ſtrong, as to remove the Cloud that hangs over us; nay, by reaſon of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the preſent evil ſo prevails, that it wholly hides the riches of their Treaſure. When S. <hi>Paul</hi> was more than ordinarily perſecuted, he needed the help of a Trance to bear his perſecution: the Promiſes alone could not raiſe him out of his weakneſſe; whence an extraordinary Viſion was added to them for his aſſurance. This pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge Saints cannot now expect, to whom is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49461:10"/>left the gift of ſuffering, but not the gift of an Immediate Revelation to find it one: We have no Mount <hi>Nebo</hi> to view our <hi>Canaan</hi> from,
<note place="margin">Deut. 34.1.</note> and thereby recompence our ſtay in the Wilderneſſe; but lye in a Valley expoſed to floods, that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm, and breathing our Vapours, that darken our Proſpect. Therefore the Soul of an Afflicted Chriſtian is for the preſent diſconſolate, and lies under the temptations of Deſpair; requiring haſtily a Mathematical Evidence of Bliſſe to overcome his ſorrows, that would otherwiſe reſt upon a Moral certainty; but miſſing a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of Faith, he is carried away with the ſenſe of ill, and neglects the uſe of his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as of a Deed dark and unſealed. But when once the pain is removed, and the dregs of Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on boyl'd off, that ſo he may freely contemplate the reaſon of his hope; his old love to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter breaks out, and in conſidence of a future poſſeſſion he can trample on all thoſe Thorns that before hindred his paſſage. Theſe are in ſhort the grounds, why <hi>no Chaſtening for the preſent ſeemeth to be joyous, but grievous;</hi> the Foundation of which Opinion you hear is Senſe; which begets in the Soul falſe apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of good and ill, miſtakes of Providence, and a forgetfulneſſe of Divine Glory.</p>
            <p>By Senſe (hitherto ſpoken of, as deſtructive
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49461:11"/>to our Faith) I chiefly mean Senſe, that is ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and unacquainted with Tryals; for this proves but an ill Pilot; and to ſet it up for our Guide in a Time of Calamity, 'tis like the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a freſh Mariner to the Holm at the riſing of a Storm, that he may make there Eſſayes of his Folly in all that roughneſſe of danger. But Senſe exerciſed with ſuffering grows valiant many times, and prepares the Soul againſt all accidents: and though it may turn into a ſinful hardneſs, (as it did in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) yet it often ſettles in judgement; whereby we come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Nature and end of an affliction, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of which is Patience and tranquility of temper: Therefore you read of the Saints re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in Perſecution; the bitterneſſe of that ſtream being loſt by a cuſtomary taſting it. That Senſe ſhould work thus, 'tis not by any Virtue of its own, but by Grace that ſanctifies it; the Dictates of this Law of Fleſh are ſoft, as its make is; pleaſure and eaſe are the two deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goods it propounds to its ſubjects; but when once the Spirit rules, it ſo exerciſes this Fleſh, that all the ſoftneſſe is worn off, whereby it can receive rougher impreſſions. So then Senſe of it ſelf is alwayes quick to mind us of pain; but the good Angel (that walks in the Furnace) keeps Chriſtians from ſcorching.<note place="margin" type="runSum">5</note>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49461:11"/>Hence it is that the grievance of ſuffering is not felt; but ſhould we once relye upon Natural ſtrength, or Phyloſophical Principles, the flame would quickly devoure us, and ſhow by our Aſhes the frailty of our Compoſition. Who can reſiſt God in that terrible Shape of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming Fire? Who can meet him when he is armed, or wraſtle with him in the ſtrength of his Power? Old Experiences and new Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings will of themſelves little avail to the curing of our wound, if God once hides his face in afflicting us; as he hides it ſometimes from the beſt of his people, to diſcover to them the falſeneſſe of their own hearts, and the terrour of his Arm. <hi>David</hi> had long thrived in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and ſharpened his Sword at the Forge of his Enemies, when he cut his way couragiouſly through the hatred of <hi>Saul,</hi> the Wars of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Invaſions of <hi>Philiſtims;</hi> but at laſt (leſt he ſhould forget whence that courage came, and looſe the memory of his own weakneſſe) God ſends him a <hi>Joabs</hi> Arrow,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.14</note> which pierces his heart with the ſame point, wherewith <hi>Abſalom</hi> was ſlain. Here he weakly complains under Gods hand;<note place="margin" type="runSum">33.</note> and the death of one Son (though a perverſe and rebellious Childe) blots out of his mind all the Idea's of former Conqueſts. If ſuch an accident were for the preſent ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49461:12"/>over a <hi>Davids</hi> Spirit; what trouble would this Spectacle have cauſed in him, had he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held Wiſdomes Tragedy, and Virtues ſudden fall? A loſſe every one is concerned in! and therefore they may find excuſe for their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
            <p>Let us take care the affliction of this place produce not worſe effects; Grief indeed we are not deny'd, for though it be a paſſion firſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſin, yet it is now purged by Chriſts weeping, and made a Hand-maid to Charity; but if we would preſerve it pure, as he left it, then the ſtream of our grief, like his, muſt be mild, and have Banks to direct it in its Flow; that ſo we may Piouſly lament our loſſe of a Perſon, whoſe Life Envy (blind and dumb as it is) yet might learn to admire; his Death Malice (hard and cruel as it is) yet might be taught to deplore.</p>
            <p>Shall I here repreſent before you his Birth, his Learning, his Travels, the Reverence of his Age, and the like? theſe were all Ornaments that belonged to him, and yet the leaſt of his Praiſe.</p>
            <p>The Nobleneſſe of his Birth was a good he little valued; nay, he ſtrove to hide it with Dignity acquir'd; as deſiring to be begotten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new by Virtue, and thence receive his Honour, which the Fortune of Birth lazily beſtows.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49461:12"/>
            <p>His Learning, as it was great and choice, ſo he uſed it only as a Servant to higher ends; bare knowledge he never doated on; nor Wit his Knowledge was ſet off with, but as they both conduced to practice; the one as the Weight, the other as the Edge of his Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>His Travels conſider'd in themſelves were common to him with others; but the mannage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe Travels was peculiar to him, and therefore may give him a Property in Fame. For they were ſo many Victories over the times, and the Vices of thoſe Kingdomes he lived in: the knowledge he had of the worlds frauds, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver byaſs'd his Soul, nor could his ſight of Sin in its ſeveral Shapes bend him from Noble De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; Who was ſuch a follower of Virtue, that he learnt from bad Cuſtomes a ſtricter practiſe of it; ſuch a Lover of Truth, that he (who was Maſter of Forreign Languages) yet taught thoſe Languages to ſpeak it? A ſtrange Current this! that has paſſed through ſeveral Lands, and yet received no Taint from the Soil, nor ever travelled from his own Nature.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The Reverence of his Age, and the Dignity of Grey Heirs, theſe were a Grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to his Perſon, but a Grace of it ſelf not to be prized; for it is an effect of Time, Folly as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49461:13"/>well as Wiſdome may partake of; but in him Age created Reſpect, becauſe it ſhow'd a Head that Crown'd it: 'Twas like an old Monument, that has NOble Acts written upon it, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Honourable for that Hiſtory. Therefore paſſing by theſe Qualities, give me leave to go higher, and conſider him in a threefold Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</p>
            <list>
               <item>As a Subject.</item>
               <item>As a Publick Miniſter.</item>
               <item>As a Chriſtian.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>As a Subject.</hi> Still times may prove hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py to a State, but not glorious to the Liver: they are dead calmes, wherein the courage and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Subject cannot move; but Heaven had ordered a Tryal of his Loyalty in ſuch an Age, wherein Loyalty ſeem'd a Crime; when Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion looked gay with ſucceſſe, and Sacriledge had Providences to gild it; yet ran he then conſtantly the hazards of his Prince, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umpht in an afflicted cauſe; as ſeeing Heavens Juſtice through the blackneſſe of its courſe, Earths ſin through its proſperous Uſurpation. Such ſervices (without worldly hope to allure) could have only pure Conſcience for their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; and it was the bare Right of his Maſter, joyn'd with a love to the Owner, made him di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt all the misfortune. This is a Quality, for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49461:13"/>which many then Liſted in as Subjects were not known, that generally fram'd their Maximes, as Seamen do their courſe, according to the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of Wind, and ſo ordered their Sails: But to oppoſe the wildneſſe of a Torrent, to ſteer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt popular Guſts, and dare good actions (as he did) though ill countenanced; this was looked upon as monſtrous in the State, whoſe great Rule was compliance with Power; whence they ordinarily proved dangerous, becauſe their Faith could not be proved. Who will commend <hi>Shimei</hi> for making one in the throng to bring back his King,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.26.</note> whom a little before in his flight he blaſphem'd? 'Twas the ſtriving of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for <hi>David</hi> made him forget his Curſes, and come with words of Allegiance in his mouth; that were as little to be truſted,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16 6.</note> as the ſtones in his hand; the one being but Treaſons cloſer work, the other an open Defiance. But flattering Arts and cunning Practiſes were far from the temper of this Perſon, who had a Breſt large and open, made indeed to hide his Maſters Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, but not to diſſemble his own Principles; whence he manifeſted them in the loweſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes, ſticking to the Crown, when it lay in duſt, and following the Sun in its Eclipſe, which the Multitude adores for its Beams. When he had thus recommended his Duty, none
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49461:14"/>could juſtly envy him in his Princes height, he ſhould partake of that Influence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>As a Publick Miniſter.</hi> Which Office he began betimes, and roſe by ſteps to the higheſt Honours of Employment; yet he never altered his courſe in his mannage of Affairs: Juſtice and Integrity were Notions fixt and rooted in his Soul; no Bribe could enter that Room; for it was before richlier fill'd, and Honeſty kept the Key; ſo that with the ſame truth he ty'd himſelf to the buſineſſe of his Prince, as he did to his Fortune. What Truſt he had in the World three Courts can witneſſe; how well he mannaged it, they may equally proclaim; for the general good was his aim, and thither he directed all his Endeavours. I need not menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the care he had of his Charge; for that was a work of his Nature, nor the exactneſſe of his performance, for that was an ordinary effect of his Wiſdome; but give me leave to declare to you the clearneſſe of his deſigns in all his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, who never ſtudied Self to enrich, but only Self to Command: His whole Treaty of Commerce had nothing of Private Traffick; for his Soul was above Wealth, and he Nobly ſhow'd it, when he threw it away to preſerve Kingdomes. To the Peace of Crowns he made his flight in this Embaſſie, and not to Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49461:14"/>Peace the great gift of Heaven, and the Nobleſt Copy man has left him for imitation; It was this endeared his labours abroad; and with this he thought to magnifie his Maſter at home, when the World ſhould ſee (by that Mediation betwixt States) the goodneſſe of our King, as in War they had felt the greatneſſe of his Power. And what could be more Honour to a Prince, than the glory of ſaving with one hand, when the other Conquered; of ſetling Dominion in Princes, when he had broke it in States? The firſt work this one Miniſter endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured; the latter a whole Fleet ſerved in: but though that good deſign of his for uniting Kingdomes (which he ſo lately ventured to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure with his own danger) be now fruſtrated by the prejudices of obſtinate men,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In his Voyage this Year to</hi> Portugal.</note> yet the fruit is not to himſelf: God looks on him as a Peace-Maker, and has accordingly beſtowed his Reward.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>As a Chriſtian.</hi> What the Graces of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity are, the Apoſtle deſcribes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23. <hi>The fruit of the Spirit</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>is love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, meekneſs, faith, temperance; againſt ſuch there is no Law:</hi> And it were eaſie for me to make out, how in all theſe he excelled. Love ruled in him as the moving Principle, and joy as the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49461:15"/>attendant of his good actions; Peace was his end; Long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, meekneſſe, were his Conſtitution; Temperance his Habit; and Faith in his God a Grace that Sanctified all. In his laſt ſickneſſe (that came upon him with a ſevere Face, like Deaths He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld, and therefore required as ſevere a Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come) that Faith and Patience he had long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore exerciſed, did then eminently ſhine. No groan, no complaint was heard to come from him; though he had a fire raging within, and Phyſitians, as Executioners, without him, Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners I mean in their Tortures, though not in deſign: And when the Fatality of his Feaver was told him, with what compoſedneſſe of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit did he reſign himſelf up to the Almighty! With what indifferency of eye did he look on, nay part with his deareſt Friends! for his thoughts were carried upward to higher Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and drawing neer his laſt (for I was an Eye-witneſſe of all paſſages to his End) how readily did he make a good Confeſſion; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing openly, he died in the Engliſh Faith, which no Son of our Church has more cordially Eſpouſed; in the aſſurance of Everlaſting Life which no Martyr has more fully received; and then giving himſelf up wholly to prayers, he breathed away the whole time in ſuch calmneſſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49461:15"/>of Devotion, that you would think he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver verſed in buſineſſe of State, but only pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed how to Dye.</p>
            <p>God knows, I have not ſtudied to deviſe him a Character; and you well know he needs none. Indeed the time, and the place, as well as the Subject, will not allow a Fiction: the Time is a time of ſeriouſneſſe, and not of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: the place is that of a Miniſter before God, and therefore a place for truth, and not for flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery: The Subject is a Subject of Worth, and not of Title; ſo that neither I can make, nor ought he to wear the vain Dreſſe of a Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Fame.</p>
            <p>One thing I have omitted in this poor De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription; which is the conſidering him in his Domeſtick Government; in the conſtant chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a Conjugal Love; (which was mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally anſwered to a height, and reſembled the ſhine of two Tapers, lighted but with one flame) in the goodneſſe of a Fathers care, in the ſweetneſſe of a Maſters Rule: but I have purpoſely omitted it; as knowing, 'tis too ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Theme both for you to hear, and me to enlarge upon; and it would only ſerve to widen the Wound, which the intention of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is to cloſe. I ſhall therefore proceed to a brief handling of the ſecond Propoſition, which is this.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49461:16"/>
            <p>Prop. 2. <hi>That the End of Gods Blow to the Patient Sufferer, is a high reward of Eternal Peace, and Repoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto we have looked upon the Rod in the Serpents ſhape;
<note place="margin">Exod. 7.10.</note> namely, in its Plague, and in its Sting: Let us now conſider it in its own; as bearing bloſſomes to invite, and fruits to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Sufferer; that having before paid Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to Nature in Tears, we may now pay Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buce to Religion in Joy. This is that bleſſed Hope ſupported Chriſtians of Old in their fiery Tryals; whence they willingly quitted wealth, friends, any their own lives: by reaſon of this Hope they counted the ſpoiling of their goods but a putting out of their Treaſure, that ſo they might gain by a removal of that Stock, which would lye dead in their hands; the fall of Friends they looked upon, but as the fall of Corn to Husbandmen, that expect thence a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter riſing. Laſtly, their own Martyrdome, but as a quicker and more violent Entry into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, a taking of it by force; which adds new luſtre to that Glory, becauſe 'tis Happineſs with Conqueſt. Thus they fortified themſelves with the expectation of a Crown; nay ſome would not accept Deliverance, that they might obtain a better Reſurrection;
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.35.</note> wherein they ſhow'd their apprehenſions of Temporal Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49461:16"/>were far different from thoſe of their Old Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Adam:</hi> for he took the Briars of the Earth for a Curſe, but they a Bleſſing; He thought the Flaming Sword a Terrour to keep him from Paradiſe; they a Light, to guide them thither. Indeed were not Afflictions rewarded with ſuch an End, Chriſtianity would appear an Unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Yoak, its Law a Bloudy Edict; and God the giver of it, a ſeverer and leſs liberal Maſter to his People, than <hi>Joſhuah</hi> was to the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> nay, then Satan is to his Subjects: for the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> obtained from <hi>Joſhuah</hi> a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Life, though not of Liberty;
<note place="margin">Joſhuah 9.5.</note> but theſe muſt ſerve under Sawes and Axes, (as ready to be ſlain) without hopes of Reprieve: Satans Subjects receive from him their Portion in this life, though they can expect no other;
<note place="margin">Luke 15.25.</note> but theſe muſt be tormented in their life time, and at laſt enjoy no other ſhadow of content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that common cooling-place a Grave. Who could upon ſuch a ſcore endure the lighteſt Chaſtening, ſo as not to cry out with <hi>Cain, My puniſhment is greater than I can bear?</hi> Much leſs can we imagine, hee'l be able to endure the Croſs for his Profeſſion; the ſhame of which, the Son of God himſelf (with all his Divinity to ſupport the Manhood) did not deſpiſe, but with an eye to his Glory, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee'l allow God the equity, and wiſdome
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49461:17"/>of a Law-giver, and the Religion he preſcribes man, as fit to be owned; we muſt neceſſarily conclude there is a certain reward reſerved to its followers, as a reaſon of their obedience. But here two things may call for our enquiry.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In what ſenſe Chaſtening may be ſaid to yield the peaceable fruit of Righteouſneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Why thoſe that are exerciſed by Chaſtening, are the great Proprietors that enjoy it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In what ſenſe Chaſtening may be ſaid to yield the peaceable fruit of Righteouſneſs?</hi> Lanſwer, not becauſe of any Natural Virtue in affliction to produce it: for that has only this proper quality to kill, as being a Sword edged with Juſtice, that never returns empty. Who will be ſo mad, as to expect Winds ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim Peace, or Tempeſts hurl him Treaſures, when the Nature of Winde is to breathe War, of Tempeſts to bring Ruine? As little fruit can be looked for from one of Gods ſevere Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which of it ſelf threatens deſtruction. Yet though it has ſo ill a Countenance as to bode Death, it cannot actually hurt Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the rigour of its Nature is reſtrained by the power of a Mediator. So the Lyon (that was hungry and devouring, and naturally made no diſtinction in its prey) yet had its mouth ſhut up at <hi>Daniels</hi> deſcending, but let looſe all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49461:17"/>its wildneſſe upon his Adverſaries; whereby was manifeſted, the fury of that Beaſt was not loſt, but only in the exerciſe over-powred. All Chaſtening, without relation to thoſe ſtripes Chriſt ſuffered, is but a ſad Argument of Gods anger that conſumes, and mans ſin that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns: Such Lectures were <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Plagues both to him and his People, wherein were read thoſe uncomfortable Miracles of Power, and no Mercy; all their Waters were Waters of Blood, that brought ruine in their taſte, and revealed to them their End; as deſtructive would thoſe waters prove, that ſurround Chriſtians, were not other blood mingled there, to make them ſound. But now ſince a Saviour has ſuffered, all the Debts of his people are cleared; the Judge reconciled, and conſequently Acts of Puniſhing laid aſide; whence their ſuffering is accepted of, as the ſuffering of Martyrs, which would otherwiſe be no better than the Paſſion of Thieves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Why thoſe that are exerciſed by Chaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are the great Proprietor s that enjoy it?</hi> To which I may reply, becauſe theſe tread beſt and trueſt in the ſteps of their Maſter; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous to be followed by man in his ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Enterprizes, is pleaſed to tye promiſes to the example; and like the Captain of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49461:18"/>lead us on, that we might be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with himſelf through ſuffering. The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of this State, <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate ſo well knew, that he took another courſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Chriſtians, by permitting them a life of eaſe and pleaſure, and an undiſturbed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the world; which in effect proved their worſt overthrow: for the Perſecutions of other Emperours rifled only their outward goods, but this took away the Marks and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of their Profeſſion. It is part of our ſervice to Chriſt, and the greateſt too to ſuffer for his Name; who though he wrought the work of our Salvation upon the Croſſe, when Man was but looker on, yet will not apply the benefit of that Salvation, without man becomes a Party by ſuffering. For can we imagine (when our Redemption coſt him ſo bloudy a Sweat to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure) that he would thereby altogether dry our faces, and ſave us the leaſt expence of Sweat to apply it? VVould he buy Heaven to beſtow it upon man, without our owning the Purchaſe? What is this, but to make Glory vile, and the bloud ſhed for it cheap; whoſe price is beſt valued by the afflictions we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure? Therefore, when our Saviour took the way of the Croſs to triumph over Death, we find he left that Croſs ſtanding for his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49461:18"/>to ſhow the Victory was finiſht, but not the imitation; and ſo requiring mans patience to Crown his work, he ſignified it was regarded by him, not as Merit of Claim, but as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Duty; not as a Pleader for life, but as a witneſs of Subjection. 'Tis this Patience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Tryals ſeals the truth of our belief, which cannot be otherwiſe known. A Peaceful Piety is the ſleep, and not the exerciſe of a Chriſtian: Voluntary Chaſtenings, as VVhippings, Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, VVatchings, and the like; are ſlight Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayes of Devotions, no real proofs; for where our fears are not aſſaulted, and the ſtrivings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin are ſecure, there is rather the ſhow of a fight, then a true Encounter. But to combat our moſt ruling and tender paſſions in thoſe loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes we bear, and dangers we undergo, to meet malice in all its forms, and Sacrifice every Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to our cauſe, this is a ſervice declares the height of our Zeal, and the ſincerity of our Faith; which being our utmoſt payment (though but two Mites in compariſon) Chriſt wills no more for Heavens Purchaſe, exalting their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue from hence,
<note place="margin">Mark 12.43, 44.</note> that we have no more to caſt into the Treaſury. I ſhall not farther enlarge my ſelf on this point; but beg leave to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with a word of Application to our ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49461:19"/>
            <p>We have here preſented a tender Object of Patience: the fall of a Head, which Paſſion tells us, reflects on this Family; but Reaſon extends it wider to Kingdomes, as the fall of a Head, wherein their Intereſt was contained. Yet ſuch perſons Deaths (like their lives) are of publick uſe, and Tryals ſent us for a general improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that we might all acknowledge the hand correcting us, and learn ſubmiſſion to the blow. This will draw out all the Vinegar from our Tears, and ſeparate the Gall, which imbitters the affliction. What? ſhall we receive good from God (which is our undeſerved portion) and refuſe ſuch an evil, which is but another Method of doing it? Shall we preſcribe Rules to that Soveraign Wiſdome how to act, that are unable to preſcribe our own remedy? But a ſober conſiderer will be far from taxing the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Divine Providence; which he knows ſhould he oppoſe, it is a fruitleſſe work, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are unconquerable; ſhould he judge, it is an abſurd action, becauſe their end is not known. Let us firſt underſtand our own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, before we ſcruple at the Phyſick given us; let us firſt find out the evil of Death, before we quarrel at the Diſpenſation. Otherwiſe we do but bruitiſhly repine; and beſides affront God at our own peril; like a fooliſh people I have
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49461:19"/>read of,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saavedra</hi> Hiſp. <hi>De Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>this.</hi>
               </note> that ſhot their Arrows at Heaven when it Thundred; but thoſe Arrows, inſtead of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing the noyſe, turned Inſtruments of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens Juſtice, by coming down upon their heads to puniſh their preſumption. Whoever he be that complaineth, let me ask him (if Grief can allow Reaſon a hearing) what evil is there in this accident, that ſhould breed any murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his ſoul. Can the chaſtening be thought grievous, to the perſon departed, or to us left behind? To him? Then Reſt muſt be Torment, and Immortality a Penance: But alas! we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not, how a good mans ſighs go away with his breath, and his tears are ſealed up with his eyes; whoſe ſoul (now freed from the dregs and contagion of body) can have no trouble, without you'l call pity one; which may be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Saints above, ſhould they behold the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes of us Mortals below. Lies then the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of this affliction upon us? So Intereſt pleads in our Grief, and not Love: But wherein are we properly loſers, when God ſends this and the like Tryals, meerly to exerciſe us for Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? The Storm that frighted S. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Ship, had not its blackneſſe from the groſſneſſe of Air without, but from a dark Cloud within; becauſe his Maſter was aſleep there: Now his and our Maſter is uncapable of ſleep; for when
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49461:20"/>he aroſe, he threw off all the weakneſſe of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity: He is now watchful and vigilant over every accident that befalls us; whence we may look upon the bittereſt ſtorm of an affliction, (ſince Mercy governs it) with as pleaſant a regard, as we look upon Dew or ſeaſonable ſhowres that refreſh the Earth with their fall. I need not I hope fetch Reaſons from Phyloſophy to cure the diſtemper of our paſſions, which Scripture can with more truth and fulneſſe ſupply us with, out of the abundance of its ſtore. The old Heathens derived their cure of Death both from the neceſſity of that blow; as likewiſe from the period it put to Senſe: and laſtly, from a wandring Immortality the Soul by it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed. Neceſſity they thought would give Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſuch a Law, ſo as to cauſe its ſubmiſſion: A deſtroying of Senſe would remove their fears, and a wandring Immortality be a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent object of deſire. The firſt of theſe is indeed ſo convincing, as may ſilence our complaints; but the two laſt (that annihilate one part of our being, and leave the other imperfect) are but poor reliefs, to ſupport us either at our own or our friends departure. Chriſtianity affords us better Medicines to heal our wound, by ſetting before us no Airy Phantome or Apparition of good, but a ſubſtantial happineſſe; wherein
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49461:20"/>the body ſhal ſhare with the ſoul in a Beatifick vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and ſenſetaſte of thoſe divine joys, that ſhall fill the underſtanding; ſo that it makes a perfect object received by a compleat ſubject, when God ſhall be the reward, and the whole man enjoy him. But we are apt to make melancholly reflections upon that ſcene of mortality Death preſents us, in a pale look, ſunk eyes, breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs body, and a dark vault to which it muſt be carry'd: All theſe are but Artificial figures of its loſs to delude our Senſe; no real tokens of it; and therefore a right Faith is not mov'd with that ſpectacle, which dwels upon another ſcene of laſting colours; for therein is ſhown the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſpring, and Vigour of a Reſurrection. This is the great ſtay of a Chriſtians Hope; and the corner-ſtone of our building; which were it wanting, all our Preaching would be vain, and all your Mourning deſperate: But being grounded in the truth of it, We hence learn to perſwade, as you ſhould learn to rejoyce with that expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation. This is that ſtate will truly inſtruct us in the knowledge of our Natures, whereas the Life we have here, and the Death that follows it, are but ill Schools to teach it us: Life (that ſwells us with an opinion of good) is but a falſe Dreſs to hide its Imperfections: Death (that breaks mans Frame, and diſorders his duſt) is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49461:21"/>a falſe Dreſs too, to hide the Glory of his riſing: but a Reſurrection (that inſtates us in a full fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of Bliſs, that takes away all our corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and a proneſs of falling into it again) this breaks forth upon a devout Soul, in ſuch beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and luſtre, that it makes all the Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of good in this Life, all the Fears of Evil in Death, to vaniſh before it. What is there then here (in compariſon of this ſtate) can be worth a minutes deſire? when the Life (we prize ſo much) begins in Tears, continues with Cares, and ends with Torments? What is there in Death (if we reflect on this glory) can claim a minutes diſcomfort? when death (we lament ſo much) has but a ſick ſtomach, in ſwallowing its prize, and will ere long throw it up upon a Land of Immortality. Go then and bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, that thou haſt left here depoſited, thy Friend, thy Husband, thy Father, thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: Is it not madneſs? like his Grief, that is troubled, he has put his Mony to the Exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to receive his own again with Uſury. For it is but a little while wee ſtay here; and while we ſtay, God tries how we uſe, and how we ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render our Talents; which if we can give a good account of at the day of Death (that great day of collecting Gods rents) We ſhall then be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up into the Clouds, that now ſeem to us ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49461:21"/>dark; and there behold the brightneſs of thoſe Saints, wee have here mournfully lamented: There wee ſhall joyntly with them ſing Praiſes, making this no ſmall part of our Song, that God would uſe ſo ſevere a method to bring us toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. One Word in the cloſe.</p>
            <p>We are now leaving this Land and our Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces together; Suffer me at the end of my Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make a plain, but true profeſſion, before a Great Judge (to whom wee muſt all give an account of our Actions) that I have endeavour'd (according to my poor ability) a faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my Function, throughout the whole courſe of this Service: To God I leave the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my heart: To you I leave the tryal of my Paſſions, the errours of my Nature, the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my performance; but if God uſes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the heart, theſe other Infirmities, I hope, Man will pardon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to God the Father, to God the Son, and to God the Holy Ghoſt, bee aſcribed, all Honour, Praiſe, Might, Majeſty, and Dominion, both now and for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
